Preliminary Guide to the Holland Holton Papers, 1859 - 1956
Duke University. University Archives
Holland Holton papers 1859 - 1956
Holton, Holland, 1888-1947
20.5 linear feet Extent: 20500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Correspondence and subject files of Holland Holton (1888-1947), relating to his roles as Professor of History and Science Education, Director of the Summer Session, and Head of the Department of Education at Duke University, and as the first editor of Southern Association Quarterly. Major subjects include the Duke University Dept. of Education and Summer Session, study and teaching of education, and the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools. English.
UA.29.02.0050
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Holland Holton Papers was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1951-1975.
Biographical Note
Holland Holton (1888-1947) served as an educator and administrator at Duke University from 1921 to 1947. He was born in Dobson, N.C. in May 1888. He earned an A.B. from Trinity College in 1907 and a law degree from Trinity College Law School in 1915. After working as superintendent of Durham County Schools, Holton became a Professor of History and Science Education at Trinity College in 1921. He served as Director of the Summer Session at Duke and as head of the Department of Education. He was active in the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools and became the first editor of Southern Association Quarterly (1937- ). From 1937 to 1938, Holton was President of the North Carolina College Conference. He married Yela D. Young in 1911; they had two sons, Samuel and Holland Young Holton. Holland Holton died in Durham on August 20, 1947.
Collection Overview
The majority of the collection is made up of correspondence and subject files of Holland Holton. The papers are grouped into four broad categories: Summer Session, Dept. of Education, Southern Association Quarterly, and Personal papers.
Subject Headings
Holton, Holland, 1888-1947; Duke University. Dept. of Education; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Summer Session; Education -- Study and teaching; Southern Association Quarterly; Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools
Contents of Collection
- Summer Session, ca. 1936-1940
  This series contains primarily Holton's correspondence as Director of Summer Session. The correspondence deals with hiring instructors for summer session, transferring credit, and other subjects. The series also features 3 boxes of bibliographies, exams, and syllabi from Education Dept. courses (Boxes 3-5). This material documents the beginning and early years of the summer session program at Duke, as well as arrangements for instructors from across the state and country to teach summer session courses at Duke.
  The materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by subject or by last name of the correspondent. The alphabetical file begins again at Boxes 15 and 16, which may reflect later accessions of material in this series.
  - A, 1935-1937, 1938, 1941, [3 folders] (Box 1)
  - Alumni Association (Box 1)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education, Report of (Motion Picture Project) (Box 1)
  - B, 1936-1937, 1938, 1941, [6 folders] (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1)
  - Blowing Rock School of English (Box 1)
  - C, 1936-1937, 1938, 1940-1941, [3 folders] (Box 2)
  - Chapel Preachers (Box 2)
  - Charlotte, N.C., Board of Education (Box 2)
  - Choir (Box 2)
  - Curriculum and Enrollment (Box 2)
  - D, 1936-1938, 1940-1941, [3 folders] (Box 2)
  - Duke Memorial Methodist Church (Box 2)
  - E, 1936-1937, 1938, 1940-1941, [3 folders] (Box 2)
  - Education Dept., [2 folders] (Box 2)
  - Education Dept. Suggested Guides for Writing a Master's Thesis (Box 2)
  - Education (course files) (Box 3-5)
  - Educational Research Committee (Box 6)
  - Enrollment (Box 6)
  - Examination for M. Ed. (Box 6)
  - Examinations, [3 folders] (Box 6)
  - F, [3 folders] (Box 6)
  - Faculty Club (Box 6)
  - Faculty meetings (Box 6)
  - Fellowship Application (Box 6)
  - Few, William Preston (Box 6)
  - Freshman Advisory Council (Box 6)
  - Freshman English Committee (Box 6)
  - G (Box 6)
  - G, [2 folders] (Box 7)
  - W. H. Glasson, [2 folders] (Box 7)
  - H, [4 folders] (Box 7)
  - Hoban, Charles, F. (Box 7)
  - Holton, Holland, [3 folders] (Box 8)
  - Holton, Holland (Personal), [2 folders] (Box 8)
  - Honors work (Box 8)
  - Hospital care (Box 8)
  - Institute on Parliamentary Procedure (Box 8)
  - I, [3 folders] (Box 8)
  - J, [3 folders] (Box 9)
  - Junaluska School of Religion (Box 9)
  - Junaluska Summer School, [2 folders] (Box 9)
  - K, [3 folders] (Box 9)
  - Kappa Delta Pi (Box 9)
  - Kiwanis Club (Box 9)
  - L, [3 folders] (Box 9)
  - Library, [3 folders] (Box 9)
  - M, [3 folders] (Box 9)
  - Mc, [3 folders] (Box 10)
  - Master's degree (Box 10)
  - Mathematics (Box 10)
  - Mathematics Institute (Box 10)
  - Medical Service Association (Box 10)
  - Methodist College Advance, [2 folders] (Box 10)
  - Miscellany (Box 10)
  - Mississippi State College for Women (Box 10)
  - N, [3 folders] (Box 10)
  - Ninety-Nineteen (9019) (Box 11)
  - North Carolina College Conference, [2 folders] (Box 11)
  - North Carolina Council (Box 11)
  - N.C. Education Association, [3 folders] (Box 11)
  - N.C. Youth Survey (Box 11)
  - O, [2 folders] (Box 11)
  - Orphanage School Applications (Box 11)
  - Orphanage Workers (Box 11)
  - Outlines (Box 11)
  - P, [2 folders] (Box 11)
  - Papers (Box 11)
  - Phi Delta Kappa (Box 12)
  - Practice teaching, [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - Preliminary examinations (Box 12)
  - Public School Curriculum Conference, 1934 (Box 12)
  - R, [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - Raleigh Elementary Education Council (Box 12)
  - Remedial reading classes (Box 12)
  - S, [3 folders] (Box 12)
  - Schedule Committee (Box 12)
  - Southern Association of Colleges, [2 folders] (Box 12)
  - Southern University Conference, [2 folders] (Box 13)
  - Southern Women's Educational Alliance (Box 13)
  - State Dept. of Public Instruction, [2 folders] (Box 13)
  - Student employment (Box 13)
  - Student grades (Box 13)
  - Students (Box 13)
  - Summer School for Orphanage Workers, 1941, [2 folders] (Box 13)
  - Summer Session (Box 13)
  - T, [2 folders] (Box 13)
  - Teacher certification (Box 14)
  - Teaching training surveys (Box 14)
  - Teaching load (Box 14)
  - Theses in Education (Box 14)
  - Theses in Education (#542; 1932 Series) (Box 14)
  - U, [2 folders] (Box 14)
  - Undergraduate education (Box 14)
  - Undergraduate Teaching Council (Box 14)
  - V, [2 folders] (Box 14)
  - W, [2 folders] (Box 14)
  - White House Conference on Child Health and Protection (Box 14)
  - Wynne, J. P. (Box 14)
  - X, Y, Z (Box 14)
  - A - J (Box 15)
  - Appointments Office (Box 15)
  - Examinations (Box 15)
  - Governor's Commission on Education (Box 15)
  - Holton, Holland (Personal correspondence) (Box 15)
  - Honors courses (Box 15)
  - Junaluska Summer School (Box 15)
  - K - W (Box 16)
  - Library (Box 16)
  - North Carolina College Conference (Box 16)
  - North Carolina Dept. of Public Instruction (Box 16)
  - North Carolina Education Association (Box 16)
  - Orphanage School Applications (Box 16)
  - Southern Association (Box 16)
  - A - C (Box 16)
  - Circulars (Box 16)
  - Conference of District Principals (Box 16)
  - Conference for Status of Teaching (Box 16)
  - D - M (Box 17)
  - Dwire, Henry R. (Box 17)
  - English examinations (Box 17)
  - Examinations (Box 17)
  - Faculty meetings (Box 17)
  - Guidance Conference, 1940 (Box 17)
  - High School Quarterly (Box 17)
  - Holton, Holland (Personal Correspondence) (Box 17)
  - Hospital Care Association (Box 17)
  - Junaluska Summer School (Box 17)
  - Library (Box 17)
  - N - Z (Box 18)
  - North Carolina College Conference, [2 folders] (Box 18)
  - North Carolina Dept. of Public Instruction (Box 18)
  - North Carolina Education Association (Box 18)
  - Orphanage and Workers, 1940 (Box 18)
  - Ph. D. degree -- zoology (Box 18)
  - Questionnaires (Box 18)
  - S, [2 folders] (Box 18)
  - Southern Association (Box 18)
  - Studies of special problems (Box 18)
- Dept. of Education, ca. 1921-1947
  Correspondence and subject files relating to the Education Dept. at Duke University and other subjects, including some material on the Summer Session. The series also includes 2 boxes on faculty hirings in the Dept. of Education during the 1920s and 1930s.
  Materials in this series are arranged alphabetically by subject or last name of correspondent.
  - Accelerated programs (Box 19)
  - Admission to colleges (Box 19)
  - Debates (Box 19)
  - Debating Council (Box 19)
  - Degree requirements (Box 19)
  - Duke Memorial Church (Box 19)
  - Duke University -- Miscellaneous papers (Box 19)
  - Dwire, Henry R. (Box 19)
  - Education by radio (Box 19)
  - Education, Dept. of, [2 folders] (Box 19)
  - Education, Dept. of-- Correspondence, [4 folders] (Box 19)
  - Education, Dept. of-- Correspondence, [22 folders] (Box 20-21)
  - Education, Dept. of-- Correspondence, [2 folders] (Box 22)
  - Examinations (Box 22)
  - Faculty, 1920-1926, [11 folders] (Box 22)
  - Faculty, 1926-1928, [12 folders] (Box 23)
  - Faculty meetings (Box 23)
  - Fraternities (Box 24)
  - Holton, Holland (Box 24)
  - Hospital care (Box 24)
  - Kappa Delta Pi (Box 24)
  - Letters, Miscellaneous, 1923-1926, [8 folders] (Box 24)
  - Letters, Miscellaneous, 1926-1928, [10 folders] (Box 25)
  - Library, Duke University (Box 25)
  - Life Underwriters (Box 25)
  - Master of Education (Box 26)
  - National Education Association (Box 26)
  - North Carolina Education Association (N.C. Teachers Assembly) (Box 26)
  - Nursing, School of (Box 26)
  - Peace Oratory Contest (Box 26)
  - Quadrangle pictures (Duke University, Trinity College: Report of the Office of Student Activities and Report of the Office of Quadrangle Pictures, 1938-1939.) (Box 26)
  - Recreation, 1920-1923, 1925-1928, [5 folders] (Box 26)
  - Research (Box 26)
  - Schedule Committee (Box 27)
  - School support in North Carolina (Box 27)
  - Southern Association (Box 27)
  - Southern Association - Memphis (Box 27)
  - State Dept. of Public Instruction, 1921-1928, 1941, [9 folders] (Box 27)
  - Statistics (Box 28)
  - Student activities (Box 28)
  - Summer School, 1941 (Box 28)
  - University reports, [4 folders] (Box 28)
- Southern Association Quarterly
  Correspondence and subject files of the Southern Association Quarterly, a journal published for the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools by the Duke University Press. Holton served as first editor of the journal starting in 1937.
  - Southern Association Quarterly, [26 folders] (Box 29-31)
  - Southern Association Quarterly, [8 folders] (Box 32)
  - Cooperative Study of Secondary School Standards (Box 32)
  - Southern Association Quarterly, [8 folders] (Box 33)
- Personal papers, ca. 1831-1947
  Correspondence, financial papers, volumes and other materials. The correspondence is mostly personal, though some professional correspondence exists here as well. Early correspondence pre-dates Holton's arrival at Duke, and includes some material about his position as a superintendent of Durham County Schools (1951-1921). Also featured are some materials regarding Holton's membership in the Duke Memorial Methodist Church and on the university's Building Committee, including Holton's correspondence with President Few about the possible construction of a Sunday School building at Duke.
  - Correspondence, 1831-1927, [5 folders] (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1947, undated, [11 folders] (Box 35)
  - Bills and receipts (Box 36)
  - Legal papers (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous materials, [8 folders] (Box 36)
  - Photographs and negatives (Box 36)
  - Miscellaneous materials, [7 folders] (Box 37)
  - Miscellaneous materials, [8 folders] (Box 38)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1923 (Box 38)
  - Printed material (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous materials, [7 folders] (Box 39)
  - Printed material, [7 folders] (Box 40)
  - Report on Studies in Teacher Education, 1941-1944 (Box 41)
  - Reports (Box 41)
  - Lander College Information Form (Box 41)
  - Volumes and printed material (Box 41)
Related Material
Summer Session Records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Dept. of Education Records.
University Archives, Duke University.